A Finding Aid to the Rudolph Schaeffer Papers, 1880s-1997, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Rudolph Schaeffer papers
1880s-1997
Archives of American Art
Schaeffer, Rudolph
AAA.scharudo
Archival Resource Key
13.3 Linear feet
The collection measures 13.3 linear feet, dates from the 1880s-1997 and documents the life and varied career of Rudolph Schaeffer, artist, designer, teacher, writer, collector of Asian art, and pioneer in the field of color study who founded the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design in San Francisco in 1926. The papers include biographical information, correspondence, subject files, writings, diaries, journals, artwork, scrapbooks, sound recordings, and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Rudolph Schaeffer papers were donated in 1991 by Rudolph Schaeffer and the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design administrator Peter Docili, and in 1999 and 2000 by James Alexander, a friend of both Schaeffer and Docili, who had been storing portions of Docili's estate after his death in 1998, with the assistance of Frances Valesco, a fiber artist and researcher. An addition was received in 2007 by William Woodworth, a close friend and caretaker of Schaeffer's and in 2017 and 2018 by Frances Valesco.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information. Use of archival audiovisual recordings requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Rudolph Schaeffer (1886-1988), a proponent of the Arts and Crafts movement, aspired to unite technology, science, and lifestyle in order to live in harmony with nature. An individual with many talents and interests, he was best known for his work in the field of color study and as a teacher and the founder of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design in San Francisco.
Born on a farm in Clare, Michigan in 1886, Rudolph Schaeffer displayed musical and artistic talent from a young age. Although he initially wanted to become a professional musician, he began focusing more on art when his musical abilities were compromised by an improperly set broken wrist. Schaeffer received his first formal art training as a high school student and then attended the Thomas Normal Training School in Detroit, where he studied music, art, and design. He continued studying independently, developing interests in calligraphy and metal craft.
In 1907, Schaeffer taught manual training courses in the Columbus, Ohio, public schools. The following summer he traveled to Paris and London. While in London he saw an exhibition of Josef Hoffman's modern interiors that had a great impact on his own design ideas. He then returned to Michigan and taught in schools close to home. In 1909, Schaeffer attended a design course in Minneapolis taught by A. E. Batchelder, director of Throop Polytechnic Institute in Pasadena. Both Batchelder and his course were strong influences on Schaeffer, as was Ralph Johnot, a proponent of Arthur Wesley Dow's design principles. In 1910 Schaeffer joined the faculty of Throop Polytechnic Institute, where he remained for five years.
The U. S. Commission on Education selected Schaeffer to be part of a delegation of twenty-five American teachers sent to Munich for several months in 1914 to investigate the exemplary industrial design curriculum offered in their secondary schools. Schaeffer subsequently expected to begin teaching at the Manual Arts High School in Los Angeles at the start of the 1914 school year, but World War I erupted while he was in Germany and his return to the United States was delayed so long that another teacher had to be hired to fill his place.
In 1915 Schaeffer was a manual training instructor at the California College of Arts and Crafts (formerly the Hopkins School), and taught design and metal crafts at the University of California Berkeley. For a number of years afterwards, he did free lance design work, taught private classes, and ran a small summer school in his Piedmont studio. Schaeffer was a visiting professor at Stanford University in 1918 when he was drafted and sent to drafting and surveying courses by the Army. Between 1917 and 1924 Schaeffer was on the faculty of the California College of Arts and Crafts where he taught design, color, handicrafts, and interior design. During this period he developed a new approach to teaching color and design based on the prismatic color wheel.
During the early 1920s Schaeffer worked as a set designer and as Art Director of Greek Theatre at the University of California at Berkeley, Schaeffer began applying prismatic color theory to set and costume design. He also designed sets for productions in Detroit. In 1925, Schaeffer saw the Paris Exposition and researched interior and stage design while in France.
The Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design which, in its early days was called the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Rhythmo-Chromatic Design, opened on St. Anne Street in San Francisco's Chinatown in 1926. In 1951 the school then moved to Union Street on Telegraph Hill where it remained for nearly a decade. In 1960, the school purchased a former boys' school on Mariposa Street, Portero Hill. Rudolph Schaeffer lived in a small cottage built for him at the rear of the property where he designed and tended a remarkable "Peace Garden."
The Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design was best known for its courses in color and interior design. Schaeffer was the first person in the United States to teach prismatic color theory, is credited with being the first to use the term "interior design" rather than "interior decoration" and the first to incorporate the use of models into interior design coursework. In 1959 the school's courses were expanded from 2 to 3-year programs and a diploma was awarded. Former students include many successful interior designers, textile designers, furniture designers, industrial designers, commercial artists, color consultants, teachers, and master flower arrangers.
In addition to the interior design and color diploma courses, the school offered a summer session, classes for children, a brief lecture series for the general public, and a wide variety of classes including advertising art, architecture and design, art history, art in public schools, calligraphy, color design, color for television, color for weavers, color theory, design, drawing, environmental aesthetics, fashion design, fashion illustration, flower arrangement, industrial design, interior design, Notan, sculpture, space planning, textile design, and weaving. Always struggling financially and sometimes lacking adequate enrollment, the school nevertheless managed to stay open for nearly 60 years. In 1984, the Board of Directors voted to remove Schaeffer from the board and close the school. Two years earlier the board had forced Schaeffer to retire, appointed him Director Emeritus, and brought in a new director charged with making the institution financially solvent, reorganizing the curriculum, and working toward accreditation. Unable to separate himself from the school (though he had done so legally when it was incorporated in 1953), Schaeffer balked and refused to cooperate with plans for revitalizing the institution.
One of the aims of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design was to interpret Asian esthetic principles. To this end the East West Gallery was established at the school in 1950. A membership organization, it offered exhibitions, lectures, concerts, and other programs that encouraged cultural integration. Exhibitions alternated between East (Asian art and artifacts from Rudolph Schaeffer's collection or other sources) and West (student work or work of local artists illustrating the influence of the Asian esthetic on contemporary art and design). East West Gallery was a membership organization, the first space of its kind in San Francisco for Asian art and operated in each of the school's locations.
In addition to running the school Schaeffer was involved in many other activities. He wrote several articles about flower arrangement, color, and color theory that were published in popular magazines. In 1935, he published Flower Arrangement Folio I (said to be the first on the subject published in this country) and in 1942 edited and wrote the introduction to Sunset's Flower Arrangement Book by Nell True Welch. Over a period of many years, he worked on several monographs on color, design, and "rhythmo-chromatics." None were ever published.
A sought-after speaker on the subjects of color, interior design, flower arrangement, and myriad other art topics, Schaeffer frequently served as a juror for art exhibitions and flower shows. From the 1930s on, the San Francisco department store Emporium used his services as a color consultant, as did Dutch Boy paints, and numerous textile and clothing manufacturers. Builders also asked Schaeffer to select interior and exterior colors for suburban housing developments.
Schaeffer worked on planning and designing the decorative arts exhibition at the 1939-40 Golden Gate International Exposition. In 1943-44, he participated in the Red Cross's Arts and Skills program, using color therapy with shell-shocked soldiers in a psychiatric unit.
The Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art began as a collection of ceramics, both historical and contemporary examples chosen for their form and color, which he used for flower arrangements and in set-ups for still life classes. It soon expanded to include color prints, paintings, screens, and other works of art and portions were exhibited frequently in the East West Gallery. Selections from this collection were exhibited in Kansas City in 1960 and at the Asian Art Museum of San Francisco in 1976.
The City of San Francisco declared June 26, 1986, Schaeffer's 100th birthday, "Rudolph Schaeffer Day" and it was observed with great fanfare. He died at home on March 5, 1988, a few months before his 102nd birthday.
Scope and Content Note
The collection measures 13.3 linear feet, dates from the 1880s-1997, and documents the life and varied career of Rudolph Schaeffer, artist, designer, teacher, writer, collector of Asian art, and pioneer in the field of color study who founded the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design in San Francisco in 1926. The papers include biographical information, correspondence, subject files, writings, diaries, journals, artwork, scrapbooks, sound recordings, and photographs.
Correspondence documents Schaeffer's personal and professional activities as well as the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. Subject files contain various combinations of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and drawings reflecting Schaeffer's activities, projects, and interests. Within the subject files is correspondence with artists, including Mark Tobey. Extensive writings include manuscripts for published and unpublished articles and drafts, notes, and manuscripts of several unpublished books including Collected Lectures of Rudolph Schaeffer on Color and Design, Color and Design, Prismatic Color Theory, and Rhythmo-Chromatics, all undated. Diaries include a volume recording Schaeffer's 1936 trip to Japan. 42 volumes of journals, compiled between 1954 and 1987, contain entries on a wide range of subjects including lists of errands, invitation lists, class notes, drafts of letters, notes including staff assignments and staff meetings, autobiographical notes and reminiscences, and musings on religion and philosophy.
The Artwork series houses artwork by Schaeffer and his students. Found are hand-made Christmas cards, designs, sketches, and sketchbooks. Seven scrapbooks document Rudolph Schaeffer's career, his school and former students, and the San Francisco art scene. They contain printed material, photographs, letters, and a small amount of artwork. Volume 3 is devoted to East West Gallery, and volume 7 documents Rudolph Schaeffer's 90th Birthday and the 50th Anniversary of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design.
Most untranscribed sound recordings (audio cassettes and reels) are of lectures by Schaeffer and others delivered at the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design.
Miscellaneous records includes a series of hand-baticked fabric samples from the Wiener Werkstatte, as well as transcripts of an oral history with Schaeffer and other interviews.
Printed material concerns the career of Rudolph Schaeffer, his school and former students, the San Francisco art scene, and general art topics. Included are articles and a book by Schaeffer, catalogs and other items produced by the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and miscellaneous items about or mentioning Schaeffer and his school. Items of note are announcements of courses taught by Schaeffer in Piedmont and San Francisco prior to the opening of his school, and theatre programs from productions with sets and some costumes designed by Schaeffer in the early 1920s.
Photographs are of artwork, people, places, events, stage designs, and miscellaneous subjects. Artwork includes some designs by Rudolph Schaeffer; people include Schaeffer, his family, friends, and students. Of particular note are a photograph of Frank Lloyd Wright's visit to the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design, and one of Rudolph Schaeffer and Imogen Cunningham. Places include interior and exterior views of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design at its St. Anne Street and Mariposa Street locations. Also included are photographs by Ansel Adams of the home of Ed and Caroline Fey.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Information, 1900-1988 (Box 1; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1906-1989 (Box 1, 19; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1907-1988 (Boxes 1-2, OV 16; 1.3 linear ft.)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1910-1987 (Boxes 2-6, 15, 19, 21; 4.2 linear ft.)
Series 5: Artwork, 1911-1957 (Boxes 6-15, 19, 21 OV 17; 0.6 linear ft.)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1933-1976 (Boxes 6, 14, 19; 0.6 linear ft.)
Series 7: Sound Recordings, 1949-1986 (Boxes 11-13; 1.2 linear ft.)
Series 8: Miscellaneous Records, 1905-1986 (Box 7, 19, 22; 0.8 linear ft.)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1906-1994 (Boxes 7-8, 15, 19, 22; 1.2 linear ft.)
Series 10: Photographs, 1880s-circa 1988 (Boxes 8-10,15, 20, 22, OV 18; 1.8 linear ft.)
Photographs; Artists -- California -- San Francisco; Scrapbooks; Diaries; Designers -- California -- San Francisco; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- California -- San Francisco; Art, Asian; Art -- Study and teaching; Art teachers -- California -- San Francisco; Artists -- California -- San Francisco; Authors -- California -- San Francisco; Color -- Study and teaching; Japan -- Description and Travel; Christmas cards; Designs; Interviews; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959 -- Photographs; Cunningham, Imogen, 1883-1976 -- Photographs; Tobey, Mark; Adams, Ansel, 1902-1984; Frey, Caroline; Frey, Fred; East & West Gallery (San Francisco, Calif.)
- Biographical Information, 1900-1988; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 10 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes educational records such as grammar school and high school graduation programs, a graduation speech, certificates issued by the Thomas Normal Training School, and a transcript of coursework completed at Central State Normal School.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1936-1974, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Notes, circa 1957-circa 1984, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Death Certificate, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Educational Records, 1900-1916; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - French Documents, 1925-1926; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Horoscope, 1929; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Identification Cards, 1943, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Card, 1908; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Memorial Service Invitations, Obituaries, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Passports and International Certificate of Vaccination, 1914-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1906-1989; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, 19
  Correspondence documents Schaeffer's personal life and career as well as the activities of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design. The earliest correspondence mainly concerns his educational background and early teaching experience, and includes letters of reference. Also included are many requests to lecture or serve on juries, letters from friends and former students, fan letters from readers of his magazine articles on flower arrangement, and correspondence relating to East West Gallery exhibitions, job prospects for students, and loans from the Rudolph Schaeffer Collection of Asian Art. Also included are correspondence between Schaeffer and Docili, long-time administrator of the Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design and exectutor of Rudolph Schaeffer's estate, as well as with Chiang Yee, Chinese poet, author, painter and calligrapher who would visit and lecture at the school when in San Francisco. Correspondence between Frances Valesco and others are from after Schaeffer's death.
  Additional correspondence can be found in Series 3: Subject Files. Letters are also incorporated into the scrapbooks in Series 6, and some of Schaeffer's journals in Series 4 include drafts of outgoing letters.
  - Correspondence, circa 1906-circa 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-23)
  - Correspondence, circa 1908-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Peter Docili, circa 1971-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Frances Valesco (to others), circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Chiang Yee, circa 1964-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Address Cards, circa 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, 1907-1988; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 16
  Subject files contain various combinations of correspondence, photographs, printed material, and drawings reflecting Schaeffer's activities, projects, and interests.
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Arts and Skills (Red Cross work at Letterman Hospital), 1943-1944, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Arts Festival, 1956-1957, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Baker, Auda, 1941-1948, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ball, Katherine, 1947-1949, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - California College of Arts and Crafts Honorary Degree (April 28, 1980), 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - California Labor School, 1944-1947, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Chang Dai-Chen, 1970, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chinese Art Purchases from Alice Boney Chinese Art, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Chinese Moon Festival, 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clements, Grace, 1953-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Color in Parks, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Color Prints, 1940, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Confucius Commemorative Day Ceremony, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Docili, Peter and Alexandra, 1972-1987, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dow, Arthur, 1917-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Dutch Boy Paint (Rudolph Schaeffer color consultant), 1937-1940, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - East-West Gallery Exhibitions, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Archaeological Finds of the People's Republic of China, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Art of Stones and Chinese Woodblock Prints, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Art of the Pictogram, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Color Block Prints of China, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Design Through the Chinese Eye, 1955-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Fat-Shan and Shih-Wan Wares of South China, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Form and Color, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Nature and the Chinese Eye, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Emporium (department store), 1935-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - European Shopping Trip (includes receipt for porcelain purchases), 1926-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Flower Arrangement, 1932-1960, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Former Students, 1927-1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51-54)
  - Freer Gallery of Art 50th Anniversary, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Furniture Design, 1930, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Furniture Fashion Exposition (student competition), 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Gardens and Flowers, 1935-1973, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Henri, Robert, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hidel, Nankoku, 1960-1969, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Hutchinson, Robert (former student), 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Huttenlocher, Faye, 1948-1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ikebana, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Iowa (Iowa State College, Federated Garden Clubs of Iowa, Iowa State Horticultural Society), 1942-1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Irwin Paint Company, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Japanese Relocation, 1943; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Kaneko, Hiroko, 1971-1988, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kartus, Sidney, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kellogg, Rhoda, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Krevitsky, Nik, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - KRON-TV "Color for Television" Course, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Liebes, Dorothy, 1939; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Macky, Spencer, 1948-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mexico, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - M. H. De Young Memorial Museum, 1957-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Munich Trip (U.S. Commission on Education group to study color in trade school Curriculum), 1914; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Association of Flower Arrangement Societies of Great Britain, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Negroes, 1943-1945, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Oriental Art Study Group, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Other Lives ? Other Times" (clippings, possibly intended for a scrapbook), 1942-1957, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Polytechnic Elementary School, Pasadena, 1910-1968, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Puccinelli, Raymond, 1957-1959, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Randall School (Rudolph Schaeffer, teacher), 1907, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "The Rock" (2255 Mariposa St., final location of Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design), 1947-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rudolph Schaeffer Day (June 26, 1986), 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Rudolph Schaeffer School of Design Closing, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)